<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cultura | fmhub]]></title>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/categories/cultura/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-05T13:11:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://fma2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Farheen Malik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[affirmation &amp; stereotype threat]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/08/wk-7-cultural-affirmation-and-stereotype-threat/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-08T18:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/08/wk-7-cultural-affirmation-and-stereotype-threat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
    In the article <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/notrocketscience/2010/11/25/15-minute-writing-exercise-closes-the-gender-gap-in-university-level-physics/#.U5N_cZRdVo1" target="_blank"> 15-minute writing exercise closes the gender gap in university-level physics</a>, the author describes Akira Miyake&#8217;s study to close the gap between male and female performance. In this study, students in a physics class participated in a simple writing exercise that asked students to think about the things that are important to them; pick two or three of these values and write a few sentences aobut why they are important. Miyake believes this &#8220;value-affirming exercise has two benefits: it break the vicious cycle of stereotype threat, but it also sets up a positive cycle too&#8221;<sup>1</sup>. This exercise is very similar to our previous <a href="http://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/week1_cultural_blog.html" target="_blank">blog post</a> on <a href="https://github.com/fma2/phase_0_unit_1/blob/master/week_1/9_cultural_blog.md" target="_blank">&#8220;Exploring your Values&#8221;</a>.
</p>


<p>
    When I think about the values described in my previous <a href="http://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/week1_cultural_blog.html" target="_blank">blog post</a>, I first feel protective, then grounded. I feel protective because the values are important to me and, when revealed publicly (a website/blog post can be public), inspire a sense of vulnerability. I subsequently feel grounded because, despite various day-to-day external demands, I am able to understand myself by reconnecting with these values&#8211;they form my identity.
</p>




<p>
    I think affirming my values can help me mediate stereotype threat. Steele speaks of the value of coaching people to make an identity less salient<sup>2</sup> in response to stereotype threat, and discussing my values likely begins this process. Because my values form my identity, I make their importance known when I affirm them; I will begin to be more conscious of their relevancy in/to stereotype threat situations. Further, because they are available for my cohort-mates to view on my blog, they are also a useful reference point when discussing stereotype threat experiences with them.
</p>




<p>
    When a situation gets me down, I usually take a step back to reflect and reassess. I consider causes for the negative feelings and how I can resolve it&#8211;whether it be a personal mindset change or a conversation with someone else. At DBC, amongst other moments of self-doubt, I anticipate there will be moments where I question my abilities or question how well I am communicating or have communicated with my peers. To counter, I think I will continue to use reflection and reassessment. Specifically, I will revisit reasons I chose DBC to connect with what I value in the program and handle the situation accordingly.
</p>


<p><small>
    <p>References:
        <li>1) <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/notrocketscience/2010/11/25/15-minute-writing-exercise-closes-the-gender-gap-in-university-level-physics/#.U5N_cZRdVo1" target="_blank"> 15-minute writing exercise closes the gender gap in university-level physics</a>
        </li>
        <br>
        <li>2)<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q1fzIuuXlkk" target="_blank"> Video: Identity and Stereotype Threat</a>
        </li>
        <br>
    </p>
    <br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
