<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[fmhub]]></title>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-23T20:11:02-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://fma2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Farheen Malik]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[thinking &amp; learning style]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/wk-9-cultural-thinking-and-learning-style/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-22T18:56:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/wk-9-cultural-thinking-and-learning-style</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Anthony Gregorc, Ph. D., a phenomenological researcher, lecturer, consultant, author and President of Gregorc Associates <sup>1</sup>, organized a model describing different learning styles<sup>2</sup>. Referred to as the Gregorc Mind Styles model, it is theory that &#8220;provides an organized way to consider how the mind works&#8221; <sup>1</sup>. The model is based on &#8220;the existence of perceptions&#8211;our evaluation of the world by means of an approach that makes sense to us&#8221;<sup>2</sup>. Perceptions impact our specific learning strengths.</p>




<p>The model considers: two perceptual qualities, concrete and abstract; and two ordering abilities, sequential and random. In regards to perceptual qualities, concrete quality &#8220;enables you to register information directly through your five senses&#8221;, while abstract quality &#8220;allows you to visualize, to conceive ideas, and to understand or believe that which you cannot actually see&#8221;<sup>1</sup>. For ordering abilities, sequential ability &#8220;allows your mind to organize information in a linear, step-by-step manner,&#8221; and random ability &#8220;lets your mind organize information by chunks, and in no particular order&#8221; <sup>1</sup>. These components pair into four combinations:</p>




<ol>
    <li><u>Concrete Sequential (CS)</u>: These Thinkers &#8220;tend to be based in reality. They process information in an ordered, sequential, linear way&#8221;.</li>
    <li><u>Abstract Random (AR)</u>: These Thinkers &#8220;organize information through reflection, and thrive in unstructured, people-oriented environments.</li>
    <li><u>Abstract Sequential (AS)</u>: These Thinkers love the world of theory and abstract thought.</li>
    <li><u>Concrete Random (CR)</u>: These Thinkers are experimenters <sup>3</sup>.</li>
</ol>




<p>It&#8217;s important to note that &#8220;no one is a &#8216;pure&#8217; style. Each of us have a unique combination of natural strengths and abilities&#8221;<sup>1</sup>.</p>




<p>I completed the <a href="http://www.thelearningweb.net/personalthink.html">Thinking Style quiz</a> with the following results, Abstract Sequential scoring highest:</p>




<p>I ___ x 4 = 36 Concrete Sequential (CS)
<br>II ___ x 4 = 44 Abstract Sequential (AS)
<br>III ___ x 4 = 20 Abstract Random (AR)
<br>IV ___ x 4 = 20 Concrete Random (CR)
<br>(insert image)</p>




<p>With only 10% of the general population in this category, characteristics of <a href="http://www.cgribben.com/psych/as.html"> Abstract Sequential Thinkers </a> include<sup>1</sup>:</p>


<p>This learner likes:
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;his/her point to be heard</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;analyzing situations before making a decision or acting</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;applying logic in solving or finding solutions to problems</li></p>

<p>They learn best when:
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;they have access to experts or references</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;placed in stimulating environments</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;able to work alone</li></p>

<p>What&rsquo;s hard for them?
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Being forced to work with those of differing views</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Too little time to deal with a subject thoroughly</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Repeating the same tasks over and over</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Lots of specific rules and regulations</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;&ldquo;sentimental&rdquo; thinking</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Expressing their emotions</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Being diplomatic when convincing others</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Not monopolizing a conversation</li></p>

<p>As an Abstract Sequential (AS) Thinker, I anticipate that, once given a project or assignment at DBC, I will likely spend time preparing and researching before beginning. Equipped with all of the necessary information, I will be able to execute the assignment without too much pain, consistently referring to the tools and resources I have collected through the comprehensive prep work. Notably, this process that I, as an Abstract Sequantial Thinker, feel the need to go through is both an advantage and a disadvantage</p>

<p>Specifically, in Phase 0, I found I did not trust my first instincts to my own detriment. This occurred when a challenge covering material that I did know was presented in a way with which I was not as familiar&#8211;either in explicated examples or in the directions or in the use of language or vocabulary terms. Instead of attempting the challenge, I needed to stop and research. Sometimes I was concerned that, if I just began to try different steps, I would waste too much time &#8211;and time was limited due to full-time work obligations. Unfortunately, I could have learned more practical applications through trial-and-error&#8211;instead, I would research theory and online resources.</p>




<p>To allow for this practical learning during Phase 1 and beyond, I anticipate it will help to have more dedicated time to DBC&#8211;this is a plan of action that is luckily already in place (with Phase 1 starting tomorrow). I believe I should also expand my use of the <a href="http://pomodorotechnique.com/">Pomodoro Technique</a>. Previously, I used the technique to time myself on a whole challenge; I can easily begin to use it to time myself on parts of the challenge, including the early steps of understanding the problem and trying to immediately apply what I know.</p>




<p>To further improve the ways I learn and think in an effort to be more well-rounded, it is important to consider what AS thinkers find difficult. For one, AS thinkers need time to deal with a subject thoroughly. To grow, especially knowing there will likely not always be enough time, I should make myself available for assignments and challenges that limit time but are within my scope of knowledge. This will hopefully provide me with opportunities to feel successful and allow me to understand that not every subject needs to be dealt with thoroughly to be done right.</p>




<p>Further, AS thinkers struggle with being forced to work with those of differing views and being diplomatic when convincing others. To improve my collaboration abilities, I should begin by listening and observing peers, those with differing views or those I want to convince. From listening and observing, I will likely gain insights and understandings about those with differing views that I could not gain otherwise. Further, I can use those insights in questions and any other points I need to make to be heard when it is my turn to speak.</p>


<p><small>
References:</p>

<p><li>1. <a href="http://web.cortland.edu/andersmd/learning/gregorc.htm">Mind Styles - Anthony Gregorc</a>
</li></p>

<p><li>2. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_styles#Anthony_Gregorc.27s_model">Wikipedia: Learning Styles</a>
</li></p>

<p><li>3. <a href="http://www.thelearningweb.net/personalthink.html">Personal Thinking Styles</a>
</li>
</p>
Other Resources:</p>

<p><li><a href="http://www.colorfulleadership.info/papers/concrete.htm"> Concrete - Abstract - Sequential - Random: Applying the Gregorc 4-Quadrant Model to Teamwork</a>
</li></p>

<p><li><a href="http://facstaff.gpc.edu/~jgutliph/Books/learning_styles/Abstract_Sequential.html">The Abstract Sequential Learning Style</a>
</li></p>

<p><li><a href="http://child-1st.typepad.com/my_weblog/2010/05/the-abstract-sequential-learning-style.html">The Abstract Consequential Learning Style</a>
</li></p>

<p><li><a href="http://www.ieslearning.co.uk/abseq.html">The Abstract Sequential Individual</a>
</li>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cheatsheet Looping Through Arrays With Ruby And Javascript]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/cheatsheet-looping-through-arrays-with-ruby-and-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/cheatsheet-looping-through-arrays-with-ruby-and-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><table class="body-wrap">
<tr>
<td></td>
<td class="container">
<table>
<tr>
<td>
<h1>Cheat Sheet: Looping through Arrays with Ruby &amp; Javascript</h1>
<h5>So you want to perform some operation on each item in an array?</h5>
<p>Below is a list of ways I most often iterate through an array with Ruby &amp; Javascript.</p>
<p>The examples below refer to the following sample arrays:</p>
<code>
<ol>
<li>students = [&ldquo;Farheen&rdquo;, &ldquo;Joel&rdquo;, &ldquo;Maria&rdquo;, &ldquo;Tanner&rdquo;, &ldquo;Sam&rdquo;]</li>
<li>numbers = [1,2,3,4,5]</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><a id="top"></a>Scroll to view examples or use the quick links below.</p>
<div class="quick-links-ruby">
<li><a href="#Ruby">ruby (top of list)</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ruby-Collect">#collect</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ruby-Each">#each</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ruby-EachIndex">#each_index</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ruby-DeleteIf">#delete_if</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ruby-FindIndex">#find_index</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ruby-For">for..in</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ruby-Map">#map</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ruby-Select">#select</a></li>
</div>
<br>
<div class="quick-links-js">
<li><a href="#Javascript">javascript (top of list)</a></li>
<li><a href="#JS-ForLoop">FOR loop</a></li>
<li><a href="#JS-ForInLoop">FOR-IN loop</a></li>
</div>
<h3><a id="Ruby">Ruby</a></h3>
<h4><a id="Ruby-Collect">#collect</a></h4></p>

<p><p>Invokes the given block once for each element of self. Creates a new array containing the values returned by the block. Can be descructive if written as
<small>collect!</small>. Same as #map</p>
<!--   <code>
<ol>
<li></li>
<li></li>
</ol>
</code> &ndash;>
<code>
<ol>
<li>students.collect { |student| p student +&ldquo;!&rdquo;}</li>
<li># => [&ldquo;Joel!&rdquo;, &ldquo;Maria!&rdquo;, &ldquo;Tanner!&rdquo;, &ldquo;Sam!&rdquo;]</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p>
<h4><a id="Ruby-Each">#each</a></h4>
<p>Calls the given block once for each element in self, passing that element as a parameter</p>
<code>
<ol>
<li>numbers.each {|number| p number}</li>
<li># => [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p>
<h4><a id="Ruby-EachIndex">#each_index</a></h4>
<p>Same as #each, but passes the index of the element instead of the element itself.</p>
<code>
<ol>
<li>numbers.each_index {|i| p i}</li>
<li># => [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p>
<h4><a id="Ruby-DeleteIf">#delete_if</a></h4>
<p>Deletes every element of self for which block evaluates to true. The array is changed instantly every time the block is called, not after the iteration is over.</p>
<code>
<ol>
<li>p students.delete_if {|name| name.length > 6 }</li>
<li># => [&ldquo;Joel&rdquo;, &ldquo;Maria&rdquo;, &ldquo;Tanner&rdquo;, &ldquo;Sam&rdquo;]</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p></p>

<p><h4><a id="Ruby-FindIndex">#find_index</a></h4>
<p>Returns the index of the first object in ary such that the object is == to obj. If a block is given instead of an argument, returns the index of the first object for which the block returns true. Returns nil if no match is found.</p>
<code>
<ol>
<li>p students.find_index(&ldquo;Joel&rdquo;)</li>
<li># => 1</li>
<li></li>
<li>p numbers.find_index(5)</li>
<li># => 4</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p>
<h4><a id="Ruby-For">for..in</a></h4>
<p>Executes
<em>code</em>once for each element in expression.</p>
<code>
<ol>
<li>for n in numbers</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;p n+= 1</li>
<li>end</li>
<li># => [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p></p>

<p><h4><a id="Ruby-Map">#map</a></h4>
<p>Invokes the given block once for each element of self. Creates a new array containing the values returned by the block. Can be destructive if written as
<small>map!</small>. Same as #collect.</p>
<code>
<ol>
<li>students.map { |student| p student.reverse.split(&ldquo;&rdquo;) }</li>
<li># => [[&ldquo;n&rdquo;, &ldquo;e&rdquo;, &ldquo;e&rdquo;, &ldquo;h&rdquo;, &ldquo;r&rdquo;, &ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;F&rdquo;], [&ldquo;l&rdquo;, &ldquo;e&rdquo;, &ldquo;o&rdquo;, &ldquo;J&rdquo;],</li>
<li># [&ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;i&rdquo;, &ldquo;r&rdquo;, &ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;M&rdquo;], [&ldquo;r&rdquo;, &ldquo;e&rdquo;, &ldquo;n&rdquo;, &ldquo;n&rdquo;, &ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;T&rdquo;],</li>
<li># [&ldquo;m&rdquo;, &ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;S&rdquo;]]</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p>
<h4><a id="Ruby-Select">#select</a></h4>
<p>Returns a new array containing all elements of ary for which the given block returns a true value.</p>
<code>
<ol>
<li>p numbers.select{ |number| number&lt; 4}</li>
<li># => [1, 2, 3]</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p>
<h3><a id="Javascript">JavaScript</a></h3>
<p> To decide which of the for loops below to use, <a href="http://www.sebarmeli.com/blog/2010/12/06/best-way-to-loop-through-an-array-in-javascript/">here</a> is a good resource.</p></p>

<p><h4><a id="JS-ForLoop">FOR loop</a></h4>
<code>
<ol>
<li>for (var i=0; i &lt; students.length; i++) { </li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;console.log(students[i])</li>
<li>} </li>
<li>// =></li>
<li>// Farheen</li>
<li>// Joel</li>
<li>// Maria</li>
<li>// Tanner</li>
<li>// Sam</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p>
<h4><a id="JS-ForInLoop">FOR-IN loop</a></h4></p>

<p><code>
<ol>
<li>for (var i in numbers){</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;if (numbers[i] > 2)</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;console.log(numbers[i])};</li>
<li>}</li>
<li>// =>
    <li>// 3</li>
    <li>// 4</li>
    <li>// 5</li>
</ol>
</code>
<p><em><font size="1">back to <a href="#top">top</a></font></em></p>
</td>
</tr>
</table></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[pairing &amp; giving feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/15/wk-8-cultural-pairing-and-giving-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-15T18:56:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/15/wk-8-cultural-pairing-and-giving-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Truth be told, pairing initially felt awkward. It meant I had to meet with a stranger via video chat and accomplish a task&#8211;which required abilities that I was initially not completely confident I had&#8211;in a short period of time. To add to the awkwardness, I was nervous I would not meet the expectations set in <a href="http://vimeo.com/76662569">Pairing is Caring</a>. Notably, I did feel like I understood the purpose and benefits of pairing in theory.</p>




<p>During the second guided pairing session, it finally clicked&#8211;I found I was finally as comfortable with pair programming in practice as I was positive about it in theory. In retrospect, I realize I had not been confident in my technical abilities and was nervous I would be more burdensome than useful. For the second GPS, a guide served as my pair, and he used simple questions when I was stuck to help me me move forward. The questions did not hand me any answers; rather, they made me think about the problem differently, which led me to quickly solve it. Perhaps it was his experience with pairing that made him such a successful guide; either way, it allowed me to experience the <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/03/17/pair-programming-considered-extremely-beneficial/">power of pairing</a>.</p>




<p>Eventually, I grew to greatly appreciate pairing, even with the occasional awkwardness of having to use video chat instead of the ideal of meeting in person. I try to avoid using cliches (sometimes because I don’t understand them as an English Language learner!), but pairing definitely showed that “two heads are better than one.” It was rewarding in so many ways, including the chance to talk out code and find I was on the same page as my pair and then eventually to solve the problem in less time than it would have taken me on my own. I was only occasionally frustrated with myself. When I saw that I was not on the same page as my pair, I felt I needed to communicate more clearly and sometimes was not as comfortable with relevant vocabulary to do so.</p>




<p>For my current full-time job, there are few formal (or informal) protocols in place for feedback. I wish there were more systems, so I unsurprisingly was thrilled to see that not only was feedback expected at DBC but there were also specific guidelines that included a rubric that asked for feedback that was specific, actionable, and kind; timelines to follow; and a check for good feedback through metafeedback.</p>




<p>It was helpful to read feedback; it often confirmed what I thought I needed to improve but also provided other ways to grow I had not considered. Occasionally, the feedback rehashed the success of the pairing session, so it was fun to relive it through written word. Further, it served to keep me accountable&#8211;I knew from the beginning that I would l likely need to spend extra time on technical aspects (as a complete newbie to web development), so, in preparation for pairing sessions, I would do this extra work to ensure there was equity of effort during the session. As a result of feedback, I also reflected on my communication style/s and considered what to remember to do or say during a pairing session.</p>




<p>I actually found writing feedback to be the most difficult part of the process. Notably, I think it is because, while I realize feedback is innately subjective, I felt this need to make it as objective as possible, especially considering the guidelines and expectation to make it specific, actionable, and kind. With that in mind, reviewing others feedback provided valuable examples of how to write good (and occasionally not so good) feedback.</p>




<p>Conclusively, while pairing via Google Hangouts is fine and receiving feedback on these sessions is great, I am mainly looking forward to being able to engage in this productive process in person when Phase 1 begins!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[test-driven development]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/14/wk-8-technical-test-driven-development/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-14T18:56:38-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/14/wk-8-technical-test-driven-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Test-driven development (TDD) is &ldquo;a software development process that relies on the repetition of a very short development cycle&rdquo;<sup>1</sup>.</p>

<p><img border="0" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/9/9c/Test-driven_development.PNG" alt="TDD Development Cycle">
<small>
    <center>A graphical representation of the development cycle, using a basic flowchart<sup>1</sup>
    </center>
</small></p>

<p>Generally speaking, the cycle includes the following steps:</p>

<p><li>(1) Decide what the code will do</li>
<li>(2) Write a test that will pass when the code runs</li>
<li>(3) Run the test, see it fail</li>
<li>(4) Write the code&ndash;just enough production code to fulfill the written test</li>
<li>(5) Run the test, see it pass</li>
<li>(6) Repeat the above process for every couple of lines of code <sup>2</sup>
</li></p>

<p>Some refer to the steps as RED, GREEN, and REFACTOR.</p>

<blockquote>
<li>1) Understand the requirements of the story, work item, or feature that you are working on.</li>
<li>2)
    <font color="red">Red</font>: Create a test and make it fail&#8211;it is expected for it to fail, as it ensures your code is working.</li>
<li>3)
<font color="green">Green</font>: Make the test pass by any means necessary. Write the production code to make the test pass. Keep it simple.</li>
<li>4)<font color="purple">Refactor</font>: Change the code to remove duplication in your project and to improve the design while ensuring that all tests still pass. Repeat the cycle. Each cycle should be very short, and a typical hour should contain many Red/Green/Refactor cycles<sup>3</sup>.</li>
</blockquote>


<p>Check out this video for more on this process:</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/HhwElTL-mdI?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>As the video describes, TDD encourages design of testable code, which means better planning leading to better results. Amongst many uses, writing testable code through TDD forces the developer to break things down (i.e. code is modular), ensures code is not too tightly woven (referred to as decoupled design), and includes methods with limited scope.</p>

<h3>Benefits of TDD</h3>


<p><li>TDD enables the developer to take small steps when writing software. Many find this practice to be more productive than attempting to code in large steps. Further, it is easier to find and fix defects in code<sup>4</sup>.
</li>
<li>Each test provides feedback to the developer that each component is working.</li>
<li>The tests also provide documentation to the developer</li>
<li>After the test passes and the code is refactored, &ldquo;it is clear that the code is finished, and the developer can move on to a new test&rdquo; <sup>3</sup>
</li>
<li>Test-driven development forces critical analysis and design because the developer cannot create the production code without truly understanding what the desired result should be and how to test it <sup>3</sup>.
</li>
<li>Reduces debugging time.</li>
<li>Overall, advocates of TDD feel <u>it leads to better design in less time</u>.</li></p>

<h3>Objections to TDD</h3>


<p><li>To be able to write better code in less time, one needs to get used to TDD before he/she gets faster.</li>
<br>
<li>The basic steps are easy to learn but the mindset takes a while to sink in. And, before it sinks in, &ldquo;TDD will likely seem clumsy, slow, and awkward&rdquo;<sup>5</sup>. It may take 2 to 3 months of full-time TDD use to adapt.</li>
<br>
<li>It promotes microdesign over macrodesign and can be hard to apply in practice<sup>6</sup>. <a href="http://beust.com/weblog/2014/05/11/the-pitfalls-of-test-driven-development/" alt="Pitfalls of Test Driven Development" target="_blank">Here</a> is an interesting blog post on these points.</li></p>

<p><small>
References:
<li>1) <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development" target="_blank">Wikipedia: Test-Driven Development</a>
</li>
<li>2) <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HhwElTL-mdI" target="_blank"> VIDEO: Test-driven development: Write better code in less time</a>
</li>
<li>3) <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa730844(v=vs.80).aspx" target="_blank">Guidelines for Test-Driven Development</a>
</li>
<li>4) <a href="http://www.agiledata.org/essays/tdd.html#sthash.yRGxurFo.dpuf" target="_blank">Introduction to Test Driven Development (TDD)</a>
</li>
<li>5) <a href="http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/test_driven_development.html" target="_blank">Test-Driven Development</a>
</li>
<li>6) <a href="http://beust.com/weblog/2014/05/11/the-pitfalls-of-test-driven-development/" target="_blank">The pitfalls of Test-Driven Development/a></li></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[affirmation &amp; stereotype threat]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/08/wk-7-cultural-affirmation-and-stereotype-threat/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-08T18:56:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/08/wk-7-cultural-affirmation-and-stereotype-threat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
    In the article <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/notrocketscience/2010/11/25/15-minute-writing-exercise-closes-the-gender-gap-in-university-level-physics/#.U5N_cZRdVo1" target="_blank"> 15-minute writing exercise closes the gender gap in university-level physics</a>, the author describes Akira Miyake&#8217;s study to close the gap between male and female performance. In this study, students in a physics class participated in a simple writing exercise that asked students to think about the things that are important to them; pick two or three of these values and write a few sentences aobut why they are important. Miyake believes this &#8220;value-affirming exercise has two benefits: it break the vicious cycle of stereotype threat, but it also sets up a positive cycle too&#8221;<sup>1</sup>. This exercise is very similar to our previous <a href="http://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/week1_cultural_blog.html" target="_blank">blog post</a> on <a href="https://github.com/fma2/phase_0_unit_1/blob/master/week_1/9_cultural_blog.md" target="_blank">&#8220;Exploring your Values&#8221;</a>.
</p>


<p>
    When I think about the values described in my previous <a href="http://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/week1_cultural_blog.html" target="_blank">blog post</a>, I first feel protective, then grounded. I feel protective because the values are important to me and, when revealed publicly (a website/blog post can be public), inspire a sense of vulnerability. I subsequently feel grounded because, despite various day-to-day external demands, I am able to understand myself by reconnecting with these values&#8211;they form my identity.
</p>




<p>
    I think affirming my values can help me mediate stereotype threat. Steele speaks of the value of coaching people to make an identity less salient<sup>2</sup> in response to stereotype threat, and discussing my values likely begins this process. Because my values form my identity, I make their importance known when I affirm them; I will begin to be more conscious of their relevancy in/to stereotype threat situations. Further, because they are available for my cohort-mates to view on my blog, they are also a useful reference point when discussing stereotype threat experiences with them.
</p>




<p>
    When a situation gets me down, I usually take a step back to reflect and reassess. I consider causes for the negative feelings and how I can resolve it&#8211;whether it be a personal mindset change or a conversation with someone else. At DBC, amongst other moments of self-doubt, I anticipate there will be moments where I question my abilities or question how well I am communicating or have communicated with my peers. To counter, I think I will continue to use reflection and reassessment. Specifically, I will revisit reasons I chose DBC to connect with what I value in the program and handle the situation accordingly.
</p>


<p><small>
    <p>References:
        <li>1) <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/notrocketscience/2010/11/25/15-minute-writing-exercise-closes-the-gender-gap-in-university-level-physics/#.U5N_cZRdVo1" target="_blank"> 15-minute writing exercise closes the gender gap in university-level physics</a>
        </li>
        <br>
        <li>2)<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q1fzIuuXlkk" target="_blank"> Video: Identity and Stereotype Threat</a>
        </li>
        <br>
    </p>
    <br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[optimizing sql queries]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/07/wk-7-technical-optimizing-sql-queries/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-07T18:56:13-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/07/wk-7-technical-optimizing-sql-queries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post will discuss ways to optimize SQL queries. I will limit it to SQL query optimization options within my current scope of understanding of SQL syntax in an effort to apply the tips as soon as possible. However, I should note that, when researching the topic, I found various other SQL query optimization suggestions.</p>


<p>SQL query optimization is important for better performance. A query is a request for information from a database. Database structures are complex, so it is not surprising that &#8220;the needed data for a query can be collected from a database by accessing it in different ways, through different data-structures, and in different orders&#8221;<sup>1</sup>&#8211;this is performed through SQL statements. What can change with different SQL statements is processing time. Query optimization is meant to &#8220;find the way to process a given query in minimum time&#8221;<sup>1</sup>. Why optimize SQL queries? ServerWatch argues, &#8220;Time is money and people don&#8217;t like to wait so programs are expected to be fast&#8221;<sup>2</sup>.</p>


<p>Here are two approaches to optimize your SQL queries with a few examples of each in practice&#8211;</p>




<h2>APPROACH #1: ONLY QUERY WHAT YOU REALLY NEED</h2>




<p><u><font face="roboto slab" color="#666666">Use the actual column names in SELECT statements instead of &#8216;*&#8217;</font></u>. &#8220;This is, hands-down, the biggest, baddest SQL optimization violation out there. If you considered &#8220;SELECT *&#8221; to be off limits in your applications, I bet that would clear up a sizable chunk of the SQL problems that applications have&#8221;<sup>3</sup>
</p>




<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">BAD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT *
    <br>FROM users;
</p>


<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">GOOD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT id, first_name, last_name, age
    <br>FROM users;
</p>




<p><u><font face="roboto slab" color="#666666">Be careful with conditions in the WHERE clause</font></u>. Write it according to what you need/what you want.
</p>




<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">BAD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT id, first name, last_name, age
    <br>FROM users
    <br>WHERE age != 10;
</p>


<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">GOOD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT id, first name, last_name, age
    <br>FROM users
    <br>WHERE age > 10;
</p>




<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">BAD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT id, first_name, age
    <br>FROM student_details
    <br>WHERE SUBSTR(first_name,1,3) = &#8216;Cha&#8217;;
</p>


<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">GOOD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT id, first_name, age
    <br>FROM users
    <br>WHERE first_name LIKE &#8216;Chan%&#8217;;
</p>




<p><u><font face="roboto slab" color="#666666">Use the HAVING clause appropriately</font></u>. It is used to filter the rows after allthe rows are selected; if you do not need to do this, then you do not need a HAVING clause <sup>4</sup>
</p>




<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">BAD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT subject, count(subject)
    <br>FROM student_details
    <br>GROUP BY subject
    <br>HAVING subject!= &#8216;Vancouver&#8217; AND subject!= &#8216;Toronto&#8217;;
</p>


<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">GOOD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT subject, count(subject) FROM student_details
    <br>WHERE subject != &#8216;Science&#8217;
    <br>AND subject != &#8216;Maths&#8217;
    <br>GROUP BY subject;
</p>




<h2>APPROACH #2: CONSIDER HOW DIFFERENT OPERATORS WORK/WHAT OPERATORS ARE APPROPRIATE</h2>




<p><u><font face="roboto slab" color="#666666">Use operator EXISTS, IN,and table joins appropriately in your query</font></u>. &#8220;Usually, IN has the slowest performance. IN is efficient when most of the filter criteria is in the sub-query. EXISTS is efficient when most of the filter criteria is in the main query.&#8221;<sup>4</sup>
</p>




<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">BAD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT *
    <br>FROM product p
    <br>WHERE product_id IN (SELECT product_id FROM order_items)
</p>


<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">GOOD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT *
    <br>FROM product p
    <br>WHERE EXISTS (SELECT * from order_items o
    <br>WHERE o.product_id = p.product_id)
</p>




<p><u> <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666">Try not to use the NOT operator.</font></u> It is much faster to search for an exact match using the LIKE, IN, EXIST or = symbol operator (positive operators) instead of NOT LIKE, NOT IN, NOT EXIST or != symbol (negative operators). A negative operator will &#8220;cause the search to find every single row&#8221; whereas the positive operator stops as soon as the result is found.</p>




<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">BAD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT name
    <br>FROM users
    <br>WHERE name NOT LIKE &#8220;F%&#8221;;
</p>


<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">GOOD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT name
    <br>FROM users
    <br>WHERE name LIKE &#8220;M%&#8221;;
</p>




<p><u> <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666">Minimize the number of subqueries in your main query</font></u>.</p>




<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">BAD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT name
    <br>FROM employee
    <br>WHERE salary = (SELECT MAX(salary) FROM employee_details)
    <br>AND age = (SELECT MAX(age) FROM employee_details)
    <br>AND emp_dept = &#8216;Electronics&#8217;;
</p>


<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">GOOD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT name
    <br>FROM employee
    <br>WHERE (salary, age ) = (SELECT MAX (salary), MAX (age)
    <br>FROM employee_details)
    <br>AND dept = &#8216;Electronics&#8217;;
</p>




<p><u> <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666">Use EXIST instead of COUNT when trying to determine whether particular data exists</font></u>. The EXIST operator will stop once it finds the first record while the COUNT operator will search for all existing records on the table.</p>




<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">BAD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT column
    <br>FROM table
    <br>WHERE COUNT(column) > 0
    <br>
</p>


<h3>
    <font face="roboto slab" color="#666666" size="3">GOOD</font>
</h3>


<p style="padding: 10px;background-color: #E0E0E0 ; font-family:Courier; border: black 0.5px solid">SELECT column
    <br>FROM table
    <br>WHERE EXISTS(SELECT * FROM customer
    <br>WHERE grade=3)
</p>




<p>Hopefully, these tips will help you get started in optimizing your SQL queries! For more, check out these resources:
</p>


<ul>
    <li><a href="http://hungred.com/useful-information/ways-optimize-sql-queries/" target="_blank">15 Ways to Optimize Your SQL Queries</a>
    </li>
    <br>
    <li><a href="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.6/en/statement-optimization.html" target="_blank">Optimizing SQL Statements</a>
    </li>
    <br>
    <li><a href="http://beginner-sql-tutorial.com/sql-query-tuning.htm" target="_blank">SQL Tuning or SQL Optimization</a>
    </li>
    <br>
    <li><a href="http://www.bennadel.com/blog/1189-ben-nadel-s-easy-tips-for-writing-better-more-optimized-sql.htm" target="_blank">Ben Nadel&#8217;s Easy Tips For Writing Better, More Optimized SQL</li><br>
    <li><a href="http://www.serverwatch.com/tutorials/article.php/2175621/How-to-Optimize-Queries-Theory-an-Practice.htm" target="_blank">How to Optimize Queries (Theory in Practice)</a>
    </li>
</ul>


<p>&nbsp;
<small>
    <p>References:</p>
    <li>1) <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Query_optimization" target="_blank">Wikipedia: Query Optimization</a>
    </li>
    <br>
    <li>2) <a href="http://www.serverwatch.com/tutorials/article.php/2175621/How-to-Optimize-Queries-Theory-an-Practice.htm" target="_blank"> How to Optimize Queries Theory in Practice</a>
    </li>
    <br>
    <li>3) <a href="http://www.bennadel.com/blog/1189-ben-nadel-s-easy-tips-for-writing-better-more-optimized-sql.htm" target="_blank">Ben Nadel&rsquo;s Easy Tips for Writing Better, More Optimized SQL</a>
    </li>
    <br>
    <li>4) <a href="http://beginner-sql-tutorial.com/sql-query-tuning.htm" target="_blank">SQL Query Tuning</a>
    </li>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[stereotype threat]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/01/wk-6-cultural-stereotype-threat/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T18:55:01-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/01/wk-6-cultural-stereotype-threat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Stereotype threat &#8220;refers to being at risk of confirming, as self-characteristic, a negative stereotype about one&#8217;s group&#8221;<sup>1</sup>. While I am familiar with some of the research on stereotype threat, I had not previously seen any of Steele&#8217;s talks. Notably, even more than any article I have read on the topic, his presentations made me realize how prevalent the issue is&#8211;how it is not limited to a specific community or space (academic, personal, work, etc.).</p>




<p>An individual may have numerous social identities, including but not limited to age, sex, religious affiliation, race, occupation, etc; Steele argued that it is possible that no two people have the same set of social identities<sup>2</sup>. The social identities that one &#8220;can&#8217;t put down&#8221; are called identity contingencies. If the social identity requires one to deal with something in a particular situation as a result of the identity, then it is likely that social identity will become more important to that person&#8211;this is an identity contingency.</p>




<p>As an example, Steele describes when he first realized he was black. Similarly, while I recall identifying as Muslim early in life, I more clearly saw myself as different from many of my peers around Christmas each year. I attended an elementary school with mostly white students in a suburb in California; I did not find it notable that I did not celebrate Christmas until I was not able to relate with my peers, serving only as a starting point for numerous other moments where I felt like an outsider. Interestingly, I related with Muslim peers outside of school with ease, a discernible contrast from the othering I felt at school.</p>




<p>While my example does not explicitly speak to stereotype threat, I feel it is necessary to begin a conversation on the issue with an understanding of social identities and identity contingencies, as both are relevant to the source of and perhaps the response to stereotype threat. Steele argues that the most psychologically impactful identity contingencies are those that in some way threaten the individual&#8211;stereotype threat is a subtle identity contingency. He cites Amin Maalouf from <u>In the Name of Identity: Violence and the Need to Belong</u>: &#8220;People often see themselves in terms of whichever one of their allegiances (identities) is under attack&#8230;whether he accepts or conceals it, proclaims it discretely or flaunts it, it is with that allegiance that the person concerned identifies&#8221;<sup>3</sup>.</p>




<p>With that said, I have felt stereotype threat in numerous situations. For one, while I love traveling, I hate airports and airport security. I identify as South Asian, Muslim, and American (born and raised), and I have been stopped for extensive searches at airports more times than I can count. What&#8217;s more, on all international flights back to the U.S. save for one, I have been subject to numerous &#8220;random&#8221; searches, sometimes at all available checkpoints. Once, while departing for the US from a country in South America, I was stopped 7 times; at some point, it stopped feeling random.</p>




<p>In this particular instance, I could not help but get angry; at the last of the 7 searches, I lectured the safety agent (sidebar: it worked &#8211; they did not search me as thoroughly as they did the person before me). Unfortunately, I also could not help but feel incredible guilt after the fact. I did not like that I had possibly validated stereotypes about the Muslim and/or South Asian community; I know had reason to feel aggressive but still could not stop feeling guilty for misrepresenting Muslims or South Asians. I feel this burden every day&#8211;at work, on the street, with friends&#8211;especially in light of NYPD surveillance of the Muslim community and related post-9/11 Islamophobia. It means I have to temper speaking up against injustices with a desire to make sure my actions or words adequately represent the Muslim and/or South Asian community while also not making the situation any worse for them. Lots of pressure, I know.</p>




<p>Beyond the Muslim and South Asian social identities, presently, other significant identity contingencies in which I feel or recently felt stereotype threat include: age at work (I&#8217;m the youngest by 15-20 years and was hired at age 25 in a career, teachers&#8217; union representative, that many do not associate with youth); identification as an activist (this video sums up the stereotype threat I feel in this respect: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aKucPh9xHtM&feature=youtu.be" target="_blank"> http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aKucPh9xHtM&feature=youtu.be</a>; and occupation while a student at an education graduate school (I had trouble participating in classes for fear the points I would make would be overshadowed by how others perceived teachers&#8217; unions).</p>




<p>To respond to stereotype threat, I think it is important to consider research on stereotype threat. Specifically, Steele speaks of the value of coaching people to make an identity more or less salient. Research &#8220;demonstrates that within a stereotyped group, some members may be more vulnerable to its negative consequences than others; factors such as the strength of one&#8217;s group identification or domain identification have been shown to be related to ones&#8217; subsequent vulnerability to stereotype threat&#8221;<sup>1</sup>. In any particular situation, group, or community&#8211;including a learning community like DBC&#8211;it would be valuable to recognize who is most vulnerable to stereotype threat as well as the cues that cause it. Our cultural blog posts on stereotype threat could be a great resource for this. Acknowledging and understanding that these threats may exist is a first step. Afterward, there should be a collective effort to ensure those who identify with particular contingencies are not feeling threatened due this association. These efforts can begin with language &#8211; as a blatant example, it is misguided to tell a class that the most intelligent will succeed on a particular learning task.</p>




<p>In the same vein, Steele describes the value of engaging leadership and using normative influence. Leaders set norms for how organizations and institutions function; they can make a space more or less identity safe. DBC seems to have a strong culture of feedback; it is not just a practice in which Boots and instructors naturally engage, it is also an organizational policy and expectation. DBC leadership has explicitly set this norm. Within it, there could&#8211;and should&#8211;be explicit attention given to making feedback identity safe. &#8220;Making feedback identity safe&#8221; involves understanding cues and mechanisms behind stereotype threat and considering how one should modify how they provide feedback, what words they specifically use.</p>




<p>To make the environment around me more welcoming, it is important for me to be conscientious and self-reflective. I hope to be (and hope that I have been in the past) purposeful with how I communicate, reflective on how it may come across, and responsive when I find I should correct myself or if I see I am able to help someone.</p>


<p><small>
    <p>Sources:
        <ul>
            <li>1) <a href="http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org/definition.html" target="_blank"> Reducing Stereotype Threat</a>
            </li>
            <br>
            <li>2) <a href="http://www.diversityinc.com/diversity-events/the-stereotype-threat-dr-claude-steele-mesmerizes-audience-video/" target="_blank"> Stereotype Threat at Work</a>
            </li>
            <br>
            <li>3) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q1fzIuuXlkk" target="_blank"> Video: Identity and Stereotype Threat</a>
            </li>
            <br>
        </ul>
    </p>
    <br>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[blocs, procs, and lambdas]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/wk-6-technical-blocs-procs-lambdas/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-31T18:55:18-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/wk-6-technical-blocs-procs-lambdas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week&rsquo;s technical blog covers blocks, procs, and lambdas. I opted to research blocks, procs, and lambdas because, while I recall using them through Code Academy, I was not able to connect them to what I have learned in the past few weeks without some Googling.i</p>

<p>Blocks, procs, and lambdas are all examples of closures. Closures are functions or references to functions that are bound to the scope in which they were created. Closures meet the following criteria: can be passed around as a value; can be executed on demand by anyone who has that value; and, can refer to variables from the context in which it was created (even if those variables are no longer in scope) (source: <a href="http://www.technicalecstasy.net/closures-in-ruby-blocks-procs-and-lambdas/">http://www.technicalecstasy.net/closures-in-ruby-blocks-procs-and-lambdas/</a>). They are helpful for: refactoring, customization, iterating across collections, managing resources, and enforcing policy <sup>1</sup>.i</p>

<p><b><u>Blocks</u></b> are the most commonly used closure. They are also amongst the few exceptions to the “everything is an object” rule in Ruby. They are considered nameless functions, and they use curly braces
<font face="Times New Roman">{..}</font>or
<font face="Times New Roman">do&hellip;end</font>syntax. They can&rsquo;t be saved to a variable - so they don’t have the powers of a Ruby object.i</p>

<p>Below are examples of blocks.</p>

<p>In Example 1, the block is just a function that takes a single argument x and prints that argument to the screen<sup>2</sup>:i
<u>Example 1</u>
i</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">each</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="n">x</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>In Example 2, the #collect! method is used on an Array with a block of code. Within the method, the block takes each variable in the array and squares it.i
<u>Example 2</u>
i</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">array</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">3</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">4</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">array</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">collect!</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">**</span> <span class="mi">2</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="n">array</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">inspect</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Though blocks are useful and syntactically simple, their namelessness presents a problem when one wants to have many different blocks to be used multiple times. To do this, the block would need to be saved as a variable. This is where Procs come in! To save a block to a variable, you have to make it a <b><u>Proc!</u></b>
i</p>

<p>&ldquo;Proc&rdquo; is short for procedure. Basically, procs are saved blocks. Because they are saved, they are objects that can be passed around. Procs can help make code DRYer. And, as previously alluded, they allow one to write a function once and then pass it to lots of different functions. A Proc is made by using Proc.new and passing a block, by Proc.new {|x| x}, or by using the proc keyword, prox {|x| x}<sup>3</sup>.</p>

<p>Below are examples of Procs.i</p>

<p>In Example 3, a Proc is used to save a function in the variable greeting; the function prints “Hello World.”<sup>1</sup>
i</p>

<p><u>Example 3</u>
i</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">greeting</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Proc</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Hello World!&quot;</span> <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">greeting</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">call</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>In Example 4, doubler is a variable with a Proc that doubles a n. The function in doubler (available as a Proc) is able to be used multiple times without rewriting for two arrays.i</p>

<p><u>Example 4</u>
i</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">doubler</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Proc</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="o">].</span><span class="n">collect</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">doubler</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1"># =&gt; [2,4,6]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">20</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">30</span><span class="o">].</span><span class="n">map</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">doubler</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1"># =&gt; [20,40,60]</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Notable aspects of procs to remember:i</p>

<ul>
    <li>A return from inside exits completely out of the method enclosing the Proc.<sup>3</sup>
    </li>
    <li>A Proc doesn&#8217;t care about the arguments passed. If you define a Proc with two parameters, and you pass only 1, or possibly 3, it keeps on trucking. In the case of 1 argument, the second parameter will have the value nil. If you pass extra arguments, they will be ignored and lost.<sup>3</sup>
    </li>
</ul>


<p><b><u>Lambdas</u></b>, on the other hand, are a more strict form of proc, though they are used almost identically like procs. Specifically, lambdas “check the number of arguments passed to them, whereas procs do not. Lambdas return differently than do procs&#8221;<sup>2</sup>.
Comparing a lambda to a proc, you can see they are syntactically very similar:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="nb">lambda</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Hello DBC! }</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2"># equivalent to</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">Proc.new {puts “Hello DBC!”}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And, here is another example of a lambda:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">names</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">[</span><span class="s2">&quot;Farheen&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Faizah&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Farnaz&quot;</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">symbolize</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">lambda</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">e</span><span class="o">|</span> <span class="n">e</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">to_sym</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">symbols</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">names</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">collect</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">symbolize</span><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1">#=&gt; :Farheen, :Farnaz, :Faizah</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>It&rsquo;s likely even clearer from examples provided that lambdas are very similar to procs. Their main differences include: lambdas check the number of arguments received and return an Argument Error if they do not match; when a proc encounters a return statement in its execution, it halts the method and returns the provided value, and lambda returns the value fo teh method and allows it to continue<sup>4</sup>.</p>

<p><small>
    References:
    <ul>
        <li>1) <a href="http://www.technicalecstasy.net/closures-in-ruby-blocks-procs-and-lambdas/" target="_blank"> Closures in Ruby: Blocks, Procs and Lambdas</a>
        </li>
        <br>
        <li>2) <a href="http://jwb.io/20130107-know-your-closures-blocks-procs-and-lambdas.html" target="_blank"> Know your closures: blocks, procs, and lambdas</a>
        </li>
        <br>
        <li>3)<a href="http://verboselogging.com/2011/09/20/proc-block-and-two-smoking-lambdas" target="_blank"> Proc, Block, and Two Smoking Lambdas</a>
        </li>
        <br>
        <li>4) <a href="ttp://code.tutsplus.com/tutorials/ruby-on-rails-study-guide-blocks-procs-and-lambdas--net-29811" target="_blank"> Ruby on Rails Study Guide: Blocks, Procs, and Lambdas</a>
        </li>
    </ul>
</p>
<br>
Other Resources:
    <ul>
        <li><a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jboursiquot/getting-closure-rubys-blocks-procs-and-lambdas" target="_blank">Getting Closure: Ruby&rsquo;s Blocks, Procs and Lambdas</a>
        </li>
        <br>
        <li><a href="http://www.reactive.io/tips/2008/12/21/understanding-ruby-blocks-procs-and-lambdas/" target="_blank">Understanding Ruby Blocks, Procs and Lambdas</a>
        </li>
    </ul>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[instance variable v. class variable]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/24/wk-5-technical-instance-variable-v-class-variable/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-24T18:54:43-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/24/wk-5-technical-instance-variable-v-class-variable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post will discuss when and how to use instance variables and class variables with Class in Ruby.
Ruby is an object-oriented language in which everything is an object. A class is the factory that builds an object. To create a class, define the characteristics of the class through methods. Then, make an instance of it; an object can be built by a certain class and is called &lsquo;an instance of that class.&rsquo;
Here is a class definition with one instance method for the class Welcome:</p>

<p><img src="https://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/images/simple_class_example.png" alt="Simple class example" /></p>

<p>Here is an instance of Welcome:</p>

<p><img src="https://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/images/create_instance_example.png" alt="Create instance example" /></p>

<p>Now, we can call the method week_five within class Welcome:</p>

<p><img src="https://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/images/call_method_example.png" alt="Call method example" /></p>

<p>Both instance variables and class variables are variables found only in instance and class methods. How are they different? Let’s take a look at a few ways!</p>

<h3>Instance Variable</h3>

<p>An instance variable begins with @. Instance variables can be referenced by any method of a particular class. They are bound to the instance of the particular class. Instance variables are initialized through the instance method initialize.</p>

<p><img src="https://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/images/instance_variable_example.png" alt="Instance Variable Example" /></p>

<p>In the example, there are two instances explicated &ndash; see comments. This makes two different objects, because both objects set different values for their instance variables. Remember that how an instance variable is defined is bound to a particular instance of the class.</p>

<h3>Class Variable</h3>

<p>A class variable begins with @@. They are shared across all instances of a class&ndash;they are found in instance methods, class methods, and in the class definition itself, outside of any method. They are initialized in the class definition itself. Class Variable is important to pay attention to when using inheritance with classes.</p>

<p><img src="https://fma2.github.io/unit1_projects/images/class_variable_example.png" alt="class variable example"></p>

<p>In the example, one class (FamilyWithNewBaby) inherits from another (Family). And, though there are two instances of the class, @@members is able to be changed between them.</p>

<p>Hopefully, this helped you understand instance variables and class variables a bit more. Other resources to explore are listed below. Enjoy!</p>

<ul>
    <li>Class and Instance Variables in Ruby: <a href="http://www.railstips.org/blog/archives/2006/11/18/class-and-instance-variables-in-ruby/">http://www.railstips.org/blog/archives/2006/11/18/class-and-instance-variables-in-ruby/</a>
    </li>
    <li>Ruby User&#8217;s Guide: <a href="http://www.rubyist.net/~slagell/ruby/index.html">http://www.rubyist.net/~slagell/ruby/index.html</a>
    </li>
    <li>Class Variables: A Ruby Gotcha: <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/class-variables-a-ruby-gotcha/">http://www.sitepoint.com/class-variables-a-ruby-gotcha/</a>
    </li>
    <li>Instance Variables: <a href="http://ruby.about.com/od/variables/a/Instance-Variables.htm">http://ruby.about.com/od/variables/a/Instance-Variables.htm</a>
    </li>
    <li>Class Variables: <a href="http://ruby.about.com/od/variables/a/Class-Variables.htm">http://ruby.about.com/od/variables/a/Class-Variables.htm</a>
    </li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[challenges with computer science education]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/24/wk-5-cultural-challenges-with-computer-science-education/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-24T18:54:18-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/24/wk-5-cultural-challenges-with-computer-science-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Society demands &ldquo;a higher level and different set of skills than schools were designed to teach&rdquo;(<a href="http://www.leadered">source</a>). Even with the addition of computers in the classroom, teaching and school structures largely remain unchanged. There are many changes that could and should be made. In general, there continue to be ongoing challenges of access, adequacy and equity of technology in schools(<a href="http://www.nea.org/assets/docs/PB19_Technology08.pdf">source</a>). In this post, I want to focus on K-12 computer science education.</p>

<p>In a 2013 report entitled &ldquo;Bugs in the System: Computer Science Teacher Certification in the U.S.&rdquo;, the Computer Science Teachers Association (CSTA) and the Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) describe a disconnect between the number of US jobs in computing and teacher credentialing in K-12 computer science education. They reference the Bureau of Labor and Statistics which found that by 2020 there will be 9.2 million jobs in the areas of Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) with more than half of these jobs in computing. They claim, &ldquo;The economic well-being of of the United States depends on computing, which in turns depends on a robust computing workforce&rdquo;(<a href="http://csta.acm.org/ComputerScienceTeacherCertification/sub/CSTA_BugsInTheSystem.pdf">source</a>). We need to provide all students with the opportunity to &ldquo;develop a fundamental understanding of the principles of Computer Science as a scientific discipline&rdquo; (<a href="http://csta.acm.org/ComputerScienceTeacherCertification/sub/CSTA_BugsInTheSystem.pdf">source</a>). In a recent report, a team at the University of Chicago found five major challenges to computer science education: a lack of shared understanding of what computer science is; a need for more comprehensive, quality instructional resources; a lack of prioritization of computer science in schools; a dearth of computer science teachers; and isolation fo computer science teachers (<a href="http://outlier.uchicago.edu/computerscience/OS4CS/challenges/">source</a>).</p>

<p>While efforts could be made to include computer science in required coursework for high school graduation, preparing teachers for these courses deserves attention as well. Computer Science teacher certification/licensure requirements differ state-by-state, with some states lacking any requirements, or even a certification option, at all. Further, the report &ldquo;Bugs in the System&rdquo; calls it a â€œdeeply flawed systemâ€ with several problematic symptoms: confusion about Computer Science as a discipline, a dearth of clear and relevant certification/licensure requirements, and a lack of agreement about what teachers should know and understanding in order to be exemplary teachers (<a href="http://csta.acm.org/ComputerScienceTeacherCertification/sub/CSTA_BugsInTheSystem.pdf">source</a>). We need to provide all students with the opportunity to &ldquo;develop a fundamental understanding of the principles of Computer Science as a scientific discipline&rdquo; (<a href="http://csta.acm.org/ComputerScienceTeacherCertification/sub/CSTA_BugsInTheSystem.pdf">source</a>).</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say we convince K-12 school systems to require computer science coursework, based on present and future job demands, at least. How can we ensure there are well-prepared teachers for these courses? It would be a monumental task to try to change credentialing/licensure requirements nationwide, but it should likely begin sooner rather than later. We could also begin to consider the following to at least begin to counter the multitude of challenges with K-12 computer science education:</p>

<ul>
<li>Assess K-12 curricula to find opportunities to include CS principles and/or specific lessons.</li>
<li>Modify K-12 curricula to include critical thinking exercises and project-based learning opportunities.</li>
<li>Work with localities and districts to reconfigure the work day to include consistent, effective professional development for teachers on technology.</li>
<li>Partner teachers and school districts with tech companies.</li>
<li>For the short term, the team at University of Chicago recommends there be strategies to help existing teachers become excellent CS teachers. Existing teachers could include teachers already teaching computer science or even those teaching related subject areas (math, science, etc.). Strategies could include consistent professional development or training opportunities (<a href="http://outlier.uchicago.edu/computerscience/OS4CS/challenges/">source</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong><em>Sources</em></strong></p>

<p>1) Preparing Students for Their Technological Future: <a href="http://www.leadered.com/pdf/Preparing%20Students%20for%20Tech%20Future%20white%20paper.pdf">http://www.leadered.com/pdf/Preparing%20Students%20for%20Tech%20Future%20white%20paper.pdf</a>
2) Technology in Schools: The Ongoing Challenge of Access, Adequacy and Equity: <a href="http://www.nea.org/assets/docs/PB19_Technology08.pdf">http://www.nea.org/assets/docs/PB19_Technology08.pdf</a>
3) Bugs in the System: Computer Science Teacher Certification in the U.S: <a href="http://csta.acm.org/ComputerScienceTeacherCertification/sub/CSTA_BugsInTheSystem.pdf">http://csta.acm.org/ComputerScienceTeacherCertification/sub/CSTA_BugsInTheSystem.pdf</a>
4) Building an Operating System for Computer Science Education: <a href="http://outlier.uchicago.edu/computerscience/OS4CS/challenges/">http://outlier.uchicago.edu/computerscience/OS4CS/challenges/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[comparing ruby and javascript]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/wk-4-technical-comparing-ruby-and-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-17T18:54:01-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/wk-4-technical-comparing-ruby-and-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With hopes of better understanding both languages conceptually, I researched Ruby versus Javascript for this weeks&#8217; technical blog. Here are my findings!</p>

<h4>Benefits vs. Drawbacks</h4>

<p>In recent exposure to both languages, I have noticed the following differences:</p>

<h5>How they define functions</h5>

<p>Javascript has two ways of defining functions: function expressions and function declarations.</p>

<p>Ruby has multiple types of functions: blocks, Procs, lambdas. Ruby also has methods and method objects.</p>

<h5>Iterations</h5>

<p>While both languages will have state, condition, and iterator in object iteration there are significant differences.</p>

<p>Javascript only has a few ways to iterate: for loops, array methods.</p>

<p>Ruby has a wealth of methods to use for loops and iterators (while, until, for, #each, #times, upto, downto, each_index). Often, there are abstractions hidden in each of these methods. It is challenging to understand all of these methods as a beginner.</p>

<h5>Attention to syntax</h5>

<p>JavaScript requires much more attention to curly braces, parenthesis, commas, and semicolon. Sometimes problems are caused by simple misplacement of or forgotten punctuation like these rather than larger conceptual problems</p>

<p>Ruby does not demand as much attention to curly braces, parenthesis, etc. It is much more minimalisitic, and it allows one to focus on concepts versus syntax.</p>

<h5>When it is used</h5>

<p>Javascript is more commonly used for front-end,client-side web development</p>

<p>Ruby is used for back-end, server-side web development</p>

<h5>Which one should you pick?</h5>

<p>I think it depends on what you are trying to do, learn, or make. Useful questions to consider at first:</p>

<p>Is it client-side of server-side? Are you a beginner? Would focusing on syntax or concepts be more helpful to you?
Next, check out how both languages rank on Hammer Principle: Programming Languages: JAVASCRIPT VS RUBY! Consider what you&rsquo;re priorities are, check to see if they have been ranked on Hammer Principle, and think about the results. This should get you started on deciding which to pick!</p>

<h5>Check out the code!</h5>

<p>Below are a few examples comparing how to write code for each.<table border="1">
                    <col width="100">
                        <col width="200">
                            <col width="200">
                                <tr>
                                    <th></th>
                                    <th>Ruby
                                        <img src="http://people.csail.mit.edu/aleks/website/arby/ruby_transparent.png" alt="Ruby" style="width: 20%; height: 10%">
                                    </th>
                                    <th>Javascript
                                        <img src="https://lh6.ggpht.com/o4rkqaUwWB65RND-ZC3Nt5PQ07chvCM8mkvCXYhvRob_Qg07cjgaLtGAefZOO8J8zg=w300" alt="JavaScript" style="width: 20%; height: 10%">
                                    </th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>arrays</p>
                                    </td>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>a = [1,2,3]</p>
                                        <p>array iteration with
                                            <small>each</small>:
                                            <br>a.each {|n| puts n}
                                            <br>
                                            <em>or</em>
                                            <br>a.each do |n|
                                            <br>puts n
                                            <br>end
                                        </p>
                                    </td>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>var a = [1,2,3]</p>
                                        <p>array iteration with
                                            <small>each</small>:
                                            <br>a.forEach(function(n)) {
                                            <br>console.log(n);
                                            <br>});
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>function</p>
                                    </td>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>def method_name (var1, var2)
                                            <br>expr..
                                            <br>end
                                        </p>
                                    </td>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>new Function ([arg1[, arg2[, &hellip;argN]],] functionBody)</p>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>if .. else statements</p>
                                    </td>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>x=1
                                            <br>if x > 2
                                            <br>puts &ldquo;x is greater than 2&rdquo;
                                            <br>elsif x
                                            &lt;=2 and x!=0<br>puts &ldquo;x is 1&rdquo;
                                                <br>else
                                                <br>puts &ldquo;I can&rsquo;t guess the number&rdquo; end
                                        </p>
                                    </td>
                                    <td>
                                        <p>if (cipher_char === from_char) {
                                            <br>result = result + to_char;
                                            <br>x++;
                                            <br>} else {
                                            <br>result = result + clear_char;
                                            <br>}</p>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                </table></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[dealing with conflict]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/wk-4-cultural-dealing-with-conflict/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-17T18:53:37-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/wk-4-cultural-dealing-with-conflict</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I began teaching several years ago, I was twenty-one years old. It was my first full-time job, and, unsurprisingly, I had trouble communicating with my supervisors Specifically, I found I was able to approach them to discuss students but drew back when I needed to discuss a personal issue.</p>

<p>This led to an emotional conflict regarding personal days. I needed a personal day for travel to a family event. In completing paperwork for the personal day, I did not provide details on the family event. Further, my supervisor preferred that her staff speak to her about personal days before submitting the paperwork&ndash;I did not speak to her but only submitted the paperwork. This disappointed my supervisor. When she approached me about this, I became upset; instead of providing her with information on the personal day or on why I did not speak to her in advance, I responded with little information and visible discomfort. She, in turn, decided that I did not need the personal day, blaming me for her decision. Beyond an issue of adequate communication, it was a conflict of styles. Though it was not required by the contract, she wanted face-to-face communication regarding a personal day (and most other personal issues). I, however, was not comfortable with talking openly about personal needs and issues.</p>

<p>I do not think my actions made the conflict better. At the time, I had already identified that I needed to work on communicating with my supervisors about personal issues. Interestingly, in the compass of shame, I self-identify as someone who is likely to &ldquo;attack self&rdquo;. I think this &ldquo;attack self&rdquo; response led me to further retreat during the conflict.</p>

<p>If I could go back in time, I would have been more conscientious about building my communication skills well before the conflict. Hopefully, in that moment, this would have allowed me to explain the need for the personal day as well as the reason I did not speak to her in advance, at the very least. The experience mostly taught me that I had a lot of work to do on myself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[what is so great about javascript anyway?]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/08/wk-3-technical-what-is-so-great-about-javascript-anyway/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T18:47:42-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/08/wk-3-technical-what-is-so-great-about-javascript-anyway</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h5>Why is JavaScript so popular in web development?</h5>

<p>JavaScript is popular in web development because it is arguably the best language for the web. Here are the top 4 signs it is the best language for the web&ndash;</p>

<h3>1. It is powerful, supporting both client-side and server-side development&ndash;the latter increasingly so.</h3>

<p><img src="http://www.nuxeo.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/111111_contentgeeks_server_side_600.jpg" alt="Javascript is not this" />
(Javascript != above image)</p>

<p>Though Javascript has been around for a long time, previously, JavaScript was limited to front end development&ndash;web pages, User Interfaces and fetching data, etc. With Node.js and Google&rsquo;s V8 JavaScript Engine, this is quickly changing to more server-side development. Effectively, &ldquo;JavaScript is quickly becoming not just the ideal language for the web, but indeed a big composition of the web itself.&rdquo; It continues to show that is a capable language, especially in &ldquo;ever-growing number of cases where asynchronous communications are necessary.&#8221;1</p>

<h3>2. It has the potential to maximize the user experience.</h3>

<p><img src="http://www.luminis.eu/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/UX-Design.png" alt="Heart Website" /></p>

<p>User experience (UX) refers to a person&rsquo;s attitude and behavior towards a product, like a website or application. Apple raised the bar for what is considered acceptable in terms of user experience&ndash;the &ldquo;success and adoption of an app is highly correlated&#8221;2 to this. JavaScript has the potential to deliver the necessary &#8220;rich, dynamic web content&rdquo; 2 that attends to user experience.</p>

<h3>3. It is supported by virtually all browsers and adapts to multiple devices.</h3>

<p><img src="http://www.vanseodesign.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/browser-logos-30.jpg" alt="what a mess" /></p>

<p>Effectively, &ldquo;millions of people run browsers that can handle JavaScript&ndash;in some variation or another.&#8221;3 It is standardized across common browsers. Further, most devices&ndash;tablets, e-readers and smart phones&ndash;have javascript language. Javascript is especially useful for devices with Apps.</p>

<h3>4. It is easy to use.</h3>

<p><img src="http://mir.aculo.us/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/doge.jpg" alt="doge loves it too" /></p>

<p>One can add JavaScript to his/her site without &ldquo;having access to a server, compiling programs, or having the browser load a virtual machine.&#8221;3 Running JavaScript is as simple as adding it to a web page and uploading the page. This is significant considering the multitude of user experience features JavaScript can add to a web page. Further, it is easy to pick up because of &#8220;the very flexible nature of the language.&#8221;1</p>

<p>Sources:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://earthintegrate.com/10-reasons-why-javascript-is-the-best-language-for-the-web/">10 Reasons Why JavaScript is the Best Language for the Web</a></li>
<li><a href="http://readwrite.com/2013/08/09/why-javascript-will-become-the-dominant-programming-language-of-the-enterprise#awesm=~oDJ1EsncbCjbYc">Why JavaScript Will Become The Dominant Programming Language Of The Enterprise</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/a/oreilly/web/news/javascript_1299.html">So, What Makes Javascript So Popular?</a></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[chefs in the kitchen]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/08/wk-3-cultural-chefs-in-the-kitchen/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T18:44:02-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/08/wk-3-cultural-chefs-in-the-kitchen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Based on the video, it seems the DBC experience will be as I had hoped. As an educator, I can appreciate DBC&rsquo;s educational philosophy of experimentation, attention to growth over achievement, opinions on pair programming, and use of problem- and project-based learning.</p>

<p>Though I am interested in programming languages, I ultimately chose to apply to DBC because of its explicit emphasis on learning how to think and problem-solve. I specifically like that Shereef described DBCâ€™s attention to engineering principles and engineering sense. Further, related to these emphases is the importance of EQ over IQ. Overall, this is a culture in which I want to be&ndash;notably, this is, in part, because it is not as common as it should be, especially in the sphere of public education. It is a culture that I know will challenge me in a different way than other educational spaces have.</p>

<p>I am excited to participate in the DBC learning environment, but I am also nervous. This is because, as an educator, I understand how impactful it can be, but I am slightly anxious that I will be out of my comfort zone. Reflecting on past educational experiences, there were almost always &ldquo;right&rdquo; answers, which I was expected to find&ndash;this is a task I know I have grown used to. At DBC, I anticipate I will have to let go of this occasional itching desire to find the right solution and appreciate&ndash;through self-reflection, feedback, metafeedback, and any other protocol or DBC or personal system&ndash;the process rather than the product.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[all about CSS positioning]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/03/wk-2-technical-all-about-css-positioning/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-03T16:08:23-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/03/wk-2-technical-all-about-css-positioning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post will discuss the differences between relative, absolute, and fixed positioning.</p>

<p>The positionproperty is important for making more complex web page layouts. Possible values for this property include:</p>

<ul>
<li>static</li>
<li>relative</li>
<li>absolute</li>
<li>fixed</li>
</ul>


<h4>Static Positioning</h4>

<p>Static positioning is the default position value for any element on a website. Elements with this positioning or no positioning will fall where they are found in the standard flow of a document. These elements scroll normally.</p>

<p>Here is an example of how it is written:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='css'><span class='line'><span class="nt">p</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">position</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">static</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Each element in the sample below is in the standard flow of how the HTML was written. The elements either have no positioning or <code>position: static</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[comparing wireframes]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/comparing-wireframes/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-27T18:55:35-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/comparing-wireframes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p>Here I consider web pages on the websites Google Drive, Twitter, and Digg Reader. While each website has more than one page, I will look at each site&rsquo;s default page, the page that appears when you go to their basic URL.
<ul>
<li>What problems does each page solve?</li>
<li>What visual challenges are there?</li>
</ul>
<h2>Google Drive</h2>
<img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-MQE5h_kZzBc/U11RZNY2WsI/AAAAAAAAT2g/DIrrHrn7PDE/w830-h687-no/Google+Drive+Wireframe+-+New+Page.jpeg" alt="Google Drive Wireframe">
<p>When I go to drive.google.com and log in to my Google account, the page that appears is Google Drive&rsquo;s &ldquo;My Drive&rdquo; page.</p>
<p>In order to understand the problems this page solves, it&rsquo;s important to first understand the purpose of Google Drive. Google Drive is an application that provides users with online, cloud-based storage space for all files&ndash;these files are accessible from smartphone, tablet, or computer, anywhere the user is. These files can be shared with friends, co-workers, etc., allowing for easy collaboration. Further, files (word processing, spreadsheet, presentation, etc.) can also be created, edited, shared on Google Drive.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;My Drive page lists a user&rsquo;s files or folders; it is the user&rsquo;s home base. From this page, a user can find documents they need to view, edit, and/or collaborate. If the document is not document is not immediately visible on the &#8220;My Drive&rdquo; page, the user can use the search tool at the top of the page to find it easily. The page is simple and looks much like a folder on a computer&rsquo;s hard drive looks with folders and setting options.</p>
<p>Despite its simplicity, there are a few visual challenges. Specifically, there is an expected learning curve for new Google Drive users. In order to understand the many uses of Google Drive, they must first add files to their Drive for any files to actually appear on the &ldquo;My Drive&rdquo; page. Further, the options (My Drive, Shared with Me, Starred) in the sidebar may not be immediately familiar, as they do not easily compare with what folders may look like on a computer&rsquo;s hard drive. In this sense, visually, the page is a challenge for those who do not understand the terms&ndash;though the page is fairly simple in design, the words could be overwhelming without an understanding of their meaning and uses.</p>
<h6>Link: <a href="drive.google.com" target="_blank">Google Drive</a>
</h6>
<h2>Twitter</h2>
<img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-WGdaT7oodYU/U11RZFH85RI/AAAAAAAAT2k/OL4CurZG4pI/w830-h687-no/Twitter+Wireframe+-+New+Page.jpeg" alt="Twitter Wireframe">
<p>When I go to Twitter.com and log in to my Twitter account, the page that appears is my &ldquo;Home&rdquo; page.</p>
<p>Twitter is considered a social networking and micro-blogging website. Users are able to send 140-character messages call &ldquo;tweets&rdquo;. On the &ldquo;Home&rdquo; page, a user is able read the tweets of other users they are following. These can appear on the Home page as they are sent, with the most recent tweet at the top of the tweets feed. Users have their own Twitter pages, on which all of their tweets are listed in order of when they were sent, and it would be burdensome for a user who wants to view the tweets of multiple users to have to go to each of their pages. Thus, it is important that a user also has the Home Page to see multiple user&rsquo;s tweets (with information on a multitude of topics) at once. Further, the Home page has a search tool to be able to find other users as well as find specific content (e.g. searching for tweets about Barack Obama after the State of the Union speech)</p>
<p>In my opinion, the main visual challenge of Twitter&rsquo;s home page is the constantly updating tweets feed. Within seconds, &ldquo;__ new Tweets&rdquo; will appear at the top of the tweets feed; after the user selects it, all of the tweets he/she was previously viewing will shift down the page and new tweets will appear on top. Though there may be images in these tweets, the majority of information presented in the old tweets and new tweets is in words. The Home page may lose impact if users are not reading any of the old or new tweets because there seems to be too much of it all.</p>
<h6>Link: <a href="twitter.com" target="_blank">Twitter</a>
</h6>
<h2>Digg Reader</h2>
<img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-0A3j4-I9FC0/U11RZNWaxXI/AAAAAAAAT2c/sPrgMjf7C18/w830-h687-no/Digg+Reader+Wireframe+-+New+Page.jpeg" alt="Digg Reader Wireframe">
<p>When I go to <a href="http://digg.com/reader">http://digg.com/reader</a> and log in to my account, the page that appears shows all articles from my subscribed feeds.</p>
<p>Digg Reader is &ldquo;a news aggregator operatd by Digg&rdquo; (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digg_Reader">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digg_Reader</a>). Users are able to subscribe to multiple sites through the Digg Reader site; they can then view news headlines/articles from these sites on a single page. Using Digg Reader makes it easy to keep track of news from multiple sources without having to go to every single news site. It is a one-stop shop.</p>
<p>If a user has subscribed to many news sites that update consisntetly through Digg Reader, the user&rsquo;s feed constantly updates. On the &ldquo;All&rdquo; articles page, headlines from all of these news sites appear in order of their posting with the newest first. If the user has subscribed to news sites which focus on different topics, all of these articles will still appear together in &ldquo;All&rdquo;. This can be a visual challenge, as it pushes too much information and too many topics onto a single screen with no images or many tools (beyond the Keyboard Shortcuts) to help the user digest the information.</p>
<h6>Link: <a href="http://digg.com/reader" target="_blank">Digg Reader</a>
</h6></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[wk 1 technical: user experience and design analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/wk-1-technical-user-experience-and-design-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-27T13:49:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/wk-1-technical-user-experience-and-design-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For Week 1, I selected the following favorite websites:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="drive.google.com">Google Drive</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://digg.com/reader">Digg Reader</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Below is analysis of these websites in terms of user experience and design.</p>

<h4>Google Drive</h4>

<p>I visit Google Drive multiple times in a single day to view, edit, and share personal andwork files. I love that I am able to access necessary files from anywhere.</p>

<p>The website has a simple design; it looks similar to a file folder one may find on a computer&rsquo;s hard drive. Further, files are easily searchable from the search tool. One can search the file name or even text from within a file. A user can also easily organize their files into related folders for easy searching and sharing. For important files, a user can use the &ldquo;Star&rdquo; tool.</p>

<p>Notably, despite this design similarity, there is still a learning curve. First, files do not appear automatically on Google Drive; there are setup and uploading steps. Google Drive also has its own format for word processing, spreadsheet, presentation, and other types of files. For example, while a user may upload a word processing document created in Microsoft Word, they will not be able to edit it in Google Drive, despite being able to see it. A new user will need to learn these rules to simply view and edit files. An added step for a new user is sharing, which has additional processes that may not be immediately familiar to a new user.</p>

<h4>Twitter</h4>

<p>I utilize Twitter for quick, recent, and relevant news and information.</p>

<p>The website has user-created content. Users share 140-character text messages called &ldquo;tweets&rdquo; with their followers and on their page, which can be made public or available only to specific users. Users can also view all tweets of followed users on their home page. On this page, tweets appear in order, with the most recent tweet on top; one&rsquo;s home page updates frequently due to constant new tweets from followers. Also, the search tool makes it easy for anyone, whether a registered Twitter user or not, to search users, tweet content, or trending information or hashtags</p>

<p>Twitter can be overstimulating due to the constantly changing tweets feed. In this way, even though the website may only have 5 or so boxes, new tweet after new tweet can make it seem cluttered. The site is used by individuals, companies, and organizations who all may distribute different types of information to followers&ndash;it seems the value of the site can vary depending on this, for both viewers of tweets and tweeters.</p>

<p>I am most excited to use Twitter during specific moments, like the President&rsquo;s State of the Union, elections, awards shows, and important international events (e.g. events in Egypt or Syria). At these moments, Twitter provides minute-by-minute coverage from a seeminly unending supply of sources that is unmatched by any news station.</p>

<h4>Digg Reader</h4>

<p>Digg Reader is another useful site for news and information.</p>

<p>The website aggregates posts from news and related websites; the user subscribes to have these sites appear in his/her Digg Reader. These posts can appear all together under &ldquo;All.&rdquo; Or, the user is able to group these sites into folders for easier reading. Either way, with Digg Reader, the user does not have to visit each of the sites in which they are interested; Digg Reader becomes a one-stop shop for news and information from specific sources.</p>

<p>To browse through content, the user can simply click headlines or they can use keyboard shortcuts. When new content is posted on the websites to which the user is subscribed, &ldquo;__ new items&rdquo; appears in the sidebar. The user can choose to update their feed to include these new items. Unfortunately, there is no visible search option for the user to search their feed for specific articles.</p>

<p>If the user is subscribed to many websites, he/she may never finish reading the content on their Digg Reader. This may make the user feel differently each time he/she uses Digg Reader&ndash;at times, it may feel like he/she wasted a lot of time on information he/she didn&rsquo;t need at that time; other times, he/she may feel they have gained a lot of interesting information after stumbling on several articles from sites they love to follow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[identifying core values]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/wk-1-cultural-identifying-core-values/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-27T00:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/wk-1-cultural-identifying-core-values</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I think of times in my life I&rsquo;ve been the happiest, the proudest, or the most satisfied, I recall all of the following values:</p>

<p>Activism AdventureAutonomy ChallengeCommunity CompetenceCooperation EfficiencyExcitement FairnessFreedom FriendshipsGrowth Helping other peopleHelping society HonestyIndependence Inner harmonyInsight IntrospectionJustice LeadershipMeaningful work MentorshipPersistance Personal developmentPublic service QualityResponsibility Self-knowledgeSelf-reliance SpiritualityTruth VibrancyWisdom</p>

<p>FAIRNESS</p>

<p>The importance of this value to me stems, in part, from my years as a teacher in the Bronx. All of my students&#8217; families were low-income, most below the poverty line. What motivated me everyday in working with my students was the desire to ensure they had/have access to the same opportunities I, a person who was just lucky to be born into privilege, was afforded growing up &ndash; I seeked fairness.</p>

<p>In general, I try to live up these values: 5</p>

<p>The last topic on which someone asked me advice was career. A friend teaches at a charter school but is interested in other opportunities in education.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
