<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ux | fmhub]]></title>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/categories/ux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-23T19:56:06-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://fma2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Farheen Malik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[wk 1 technical: user experience and design analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/wk-1-technical-user-experience-and-design-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-27T13:49:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/wk-1-technical-user-experience-and-design-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For Week 1, I selected the following favorite websites:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="drive.google.com">Google Drive</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://digg.com/reader">Digg Reader</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Below is analysis of these websites in terms of user experience and design.</p>

<h4>Google Drive</h4>

<p>I visit Google Drive multiple times in a single day to view, edit, and share personal andwork files. I love that I am able to access necessary files from anywhere.</p>

<p>The website has a simple design; it looks similar to a file folder one may find on a computer&rsquo;s hard drive. Further, files are easily searchable from the search tool. One can search the file name or even text from within a file. A user can also easily organize their files into related folders for easy searching and sharing. For important files, a user can use the &ldquo;Star&rdquo; tool.</p>

<p>Notably, despite this design similarity, there is still a learning curve. First, files do not appear automatically on Google Drive; there are setup and uploading steps. Google Drive also has its own format for word processing, spreadsheet, presentation, and other types of files. For example, while a user may upload a word processing document created in Microsoft Word, they will not be able to edit it in Google Drive, despite being able to see it. A new user will need to learn these rules to simply view and edit files. An added step for a new user is sharing, which has additional processes that may not be immediately familiar to a new user.</p>

<h4>Twitter</h4>

<p>I utilize Twitter for quick, recent, and relevant news and information.</p>

<p>The website has user-created content. Users share 140-character text messages called &ldquo;tweets&rdquo; with their followers and on their page, which can be made public or available only to specific users. Users can also view all tweets of followed users on their home page. On this page, tweets appear in order, with the most recent tweet on top; one&rsquo;s home page updates frequently due to constant new tweets from followers. Also, the search tool makes it easy for anyone, whether a registered Twitter user or not, to search users, tweet content, or trending information or hashtags</p>

<p>Twitter can be overstimulating due to the constantly changing tweets feed. In this way, even though the website may only have 5 or so boxes, new tweet after new tweet can make it seem cluttered. The site is used by individuals, companies, and organizations who all may distribute different types of information to followers&ndash;it seems the value of the site can vary depending on this, for both viewers of tweets and tweeters.</p>

<p>I am most excited to use Twitter during specific moments, like the President&rsquo;s State of the Union, elections, awards shows, and important international events (e.g. events in Egypt or Syria). At these moments, Twitter provides minute-by-minute coverage from a seeminly unending supply of sources that is unmatched by any news station.</p>

<h4>Digg Reader</h4>

<p>Digg Reader is another useful site for news and information.</p>

<p>The website aggregates posts from news and related websites; the user subscribes to have these sites appear in his/her Digg Reader. These posts can appear all together under &ldquo;All.&rdquo; Or, the user is able to group these sites into folders for easier reading. Either way, with Digg Reader, the user does not have to visit each of the sites in which they are interested; Digg Reader becomes a one-stop shop for news and information from specific sources.</p>

<p>To browse through content, the user can simply click headlines or they can use keyboard shortcuts. When new content is posted on the websites to which the user is subscribed, &ldquo;__ new items&rdquo; appears in the sidebar. The user can choose to update their feed to include these new items. Unfortunately, there is no visible search option for the user to search their feed for specific articles.</p>

<p>If the user is subscribed to many websites, he/she may never finish reading the content on their Digg Reader. This may make the user feel differently each time he/she uses Digg Reader&ndash;at times, it may feel like he/she wasted a lot of time on information he/she didn&rsquo;t need at that time; other times, he/she may feel they have gained a lot of interesting information after stumbling on several articles from sites they love to follow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
