<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pair-programming | < code switch with farheen />]]></title>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/categories/pair-programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-12T13:26:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://fma2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Farheen Malik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[pairing &amp; giving feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/15/wk-8-cultural-pairing-and-giving-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-15T18:56:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/15/wk-8-cultural-pairing-and-giving-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Truth be told, pairing initially felt awkward. It meant I had to meet with a stranger via video chat and accomplish a task&#8211;which required abilities that I was initially not completely confident I had&#8211;in a short period of time. To add to the awkwardness, I was nervous I would not meet the expectations set in <a href="http://vimeo.com/76662569">Pairing is Caring</a>. Notably, I did feel like I understood the purpose and benefits of pairing in theory.</p>




<p>During the second guided pairing session, it finally clicked&#8211;I found I was finally as comfortable with pair programming in practice as I was positive about it in theory. In retrospect, I realize I had not been confident in my technical abilities and was nervous I would be more burdensome than useful. For the second GPS, a guide served as my pair, and he used simple questions when I was stuck to help me me move forward. The questions did not hand me any answers; rather, they made me think about the problem differently, which led me to quickly solve it. Perhaps it was his experience with pairing that made him such a successful guide; either way, it allowed me to experience the <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/03/17/pair-programming-considered-extremely-beneficial/">power of pairing</a>.</p>




<p>Eventually, I grew to greatly appreciate pairing, even with the occasional awkwardness of having to use video chat instead of the ideal of meeting in person. I try to avoid using cliches (sometimes because I don’t understand them as an English Language learner!), but pairing definitely showed that “two heads are better than one.” It was rewarding in so many ways, including the chance to talk out code and find I was on the same page as my pair and then eventually to solve the problem in less time than it would have taken me on my own. I was only occasionally frustrated with myself. When I saw that I was not on the same page as my pair, I felt I needed to communicate more clearly and sometimes was not as comfortable with relevant vocabulary to do so.</p>




<p>For my current full-time job, there are few formal (or informal) protocols in place for feedback. I wish there were more systems, so I unsurprisingly was thrilled to see that not only was feedback expected at DBC but there were also specific guidelines that included a rubric that asked for feedback that was specific, actionable, and kind; timelines to follow; and a check for good feedback through metafeedback.</p>




<p>It was helpful to read feedback; it often confirmed what I thought I needed to improve but also provided other ways to grow I had not considered. Occasionally, the feedback rehashed the success of the pairing session, so it was fun to relive it through written word. Further, it served to keep me accountable&#8211;I knew from the beginning that I would l likely need to spend extra time on technical aspects (as a complete newbie to web development), so, in preparation for pairing sessions, I would do this extra work to ensure there was equity of effort during the session. As a result of feedback, I also reflected on my communication style/s and considered what to remember to do or say during a pairing session.</p>




<p>I actually found writing feedback to be the most difficult part of the process. Notably, I think it is because, while I realize feedback is innately subjective, I felt this need to make it as objective as possible, especially considering the guidelines and expectation to make it specific, actionable, and kind. With that in mind, reviewing others feedback provided valuable examples of how to write good (and occasionally not so good) feedback.</p>




<p>Conclusively, while pairing via Google Hangouts is fine and receiving feedback on these sessions is great, I am mainly looking forward to being able to engage in this productive process in person when Phase 1 begins!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
