<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conflict | fmhub]]></title>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/categories/conflict/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-23T20:17:44-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://fma2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Farheen Malik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[dealing with conflict]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/wk-4-cultural-dealing-with-conflict/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-17T18:53:37-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/wk-4-cultural-dealing-with-conflict</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I began teaching several years ago, I was twenty-one years old. It was my first full-time job, and, unsurprisingly, I had trouble communicating with my supervisors Specifically, I found I was able to approach them to discuss students but drew back when I needed to discuss a personal issue.</p>

<p>This led to an emotional conflict regarding personal days. I needed a personal day for travel to a family event. In completing paperwork for the personal day, I did not provide details on the family event. Further, my supervisor preferred that her staff speak to her about personal days before submitting the paperwork&ndash;I did not speak to her but only submitted the paperwork. This disappointed my supervisor. When she approached me about this, I became upset; instead of providing her with information on the personal day or on why I did not speak to her in advance, I responded with little information and visible discomfort. She, in turn, decided that I did not need the personal day, blaming me for her decision. Beyond an issue of adequate communication, it was a conflict of styles. Though it was not required by the contract, she wanted face-to-face communication regarding a personal day (and most other personal issues). I, however, was not comfortable with talking openly about personal needs and issues.</p>

<p>I do not think my actions made the conflict better. At the time, I had already identified that I needed to work on communicating with my supervisors about personal issues. Interestingly, in the compass of shame, I self-identify as someone who is likely to &ldquo;attack self&rdquo;. I think this &ldquo;attack self&rdquo; response led me to further retreat during the conflict.</p>

<p>If I could go back in time, I would have been more conscientious about building my communication skills well before the conflict. Hopefully, in that moment, this would have allowed me to explain the need for the personal day as well as the reason I did not speak to her in advance, at the very least. The experience mostly taught me that I had a lot of work to do on myself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
