<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thinking style | fmhub]]></title>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/categories/thinking-style/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-05T13:08:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://fma2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Farheen Malik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[thinking &amp; learning style]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/wk-9-cultural-thinking-and-learning-style/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-22T18:56:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/06/22/wk-9-cultural-thinking-and-learning-style</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Anthony Gregorc, Ph. D., a phenomenological researcher, lecturer, consultant, author and President of Gregorc Associates <sup>1</sup>, organized a model describing different learning styles<sup>2</sup>. Referred to as the Gregorc Mind Styles model, it is theory that &#8220;provides an organized way to consider how the mind works&#8221; <sup>1</sup>. The model is based on &#8220;the existence of perceptions&#8211;our evaluation of the world by means of an approach that makes sense to us&#8221;<sup>2</sup>. Perceptions impact our specific learning strengths.</p>




<p>The model considers: two perceptual qualities, concrete and abstract; and two ordering abilities, sequential and random. In regards to perceptual qualities, concrete quality &#8220;enables you to register information directly through your five senses&#8221;, while abstract quality &#8220;allows you to visualize, to conceive ideas, and to understand or believe that which you cannot actually see&#8221;<sup>1</sup>. For ordering abilities, sequential ability &#8220;allows your mind to organize information in a linear, step-by-step manner,&#8221; and random ability &#8220;lets your mind organize information by chunks, and in no particular order&#8221; <sup>1</sup>. These components pair into four combinations:</p>




<ol>
    <li><u>Concrete Sequential (CS)</u>: These Thinkers &#8220;tend to be based in reality. They process information in an ordered, sequential, linear way&#8221;.</li>
    <li><u>Abstract Random (AR)</u>: These Thinkers &#8220;organize information through reflection, and thrive in unstructured, people-oriented environments.</li>
    <li><u>Abstract Sequential (AS)</u>: These Thinkers love the world of theory and abstract thought.</li>
    <li><u>Concrete Random (CR)</u>: These Thinkers are experimenters <sup>3</sup>.</li>
</ol>




<p>It&#8217;s important to note that &#8220;no one is a &#8216;pure&#8217; style. Each of us have a unique combination of natural strengths and abilities&#8221;<sup>1</sup>.</p>




<p>I completed the <a href="http://www.thelearningweb.net/personalthink.html">Thinking Style quiz</a> with the following results, Abstract Sequential scoring highest:</p>




<p>I ___ x 4 = 36 Concrete Sequential (CS)
<br>II ___ x 4 = 44 Abstract Sequential (AS)
<br>III ___ x 4 = 20 Abstract Random (AR)
<br>IV ___ x 4 = 20 Concrete Random (CR)
<br>(insert image)</p>




<p>With only 10% of the general population in this category, characteristics of <a href="http://www.cgribben.com/psych/as.html"> Abstract Sequential Thinkers </a> include<sup>1</sup>:</p>


<p>This learner likes:
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;his/her point to be heard</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;analyzing situations before making a decision or acting</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;applying logic in solving or finding solutions to problems</li></p>

<p>They learn best when:
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;they have access to experts or references</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;placed in stimulating environments</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;able to work alone</li></p>

<p>What&rsquo;s hard for them?
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Being forced to work with those of differing views</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Too little time to deal with a subject thoroughly</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Repeating the same tasks over and over</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Lots of specific rules and regulations</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;&ldquo;sentimental&rdquo; thinking</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Expressing their emotions</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Being diplomatic when convincing others</li>
<li>&nbsp;&nbsp;Not monopolizing a conversation</li></p>

<p>As an Abstract Sequential (AS) Thinker, I anticipate that, once given a project or assignment at DBC, I will likely spend time preparing and researching before beginning. Equipped with all of the necessary information, I will be able to execute the assignment without too much pain, consistently referring to the tools and resources I have collected through the comprehensive prep work. Notably, this process that I, as an Abstract Sequantial Thinker, feel the need to go through is both an advantage and a disadvantage</p>

<p>Specifically, in Phase 0, I found I did not trust my first instincts to my own detriment. This occurred when a challenge covering material that I did know was presented in a way with which I was not as familiar&#8211;either in explicated examples or in the directions or in the use of language or vocabulary terms. Instead of attempting the challenge, I needed to stop and research. Sometimes I was concerned that, if I just began to try different steps, I would waste too much time &#8211;and time was limited due to full-time work obligations. Unfortunately, I could have learned more practical applications through trial-and-error&#8211;instead, I would research theory and online resources.</p>




<p>To allow for this practical learning during Phase 1 and beyond, I anticipate it will help to have more dedicated time to DBC&#8211;this is a plan of action that is luckily already in place (with Phase 1 starting tomorrow). I believe I should also expand my use of the <a href="http://pomodorotechnique.com/">Pomodoro Technique</a>. Previously, I used the technique to time myself on a whole challenge; I can easily begin to use it to time myself on parts of the challenge, including the early steps of understanding the problem and trying to immediately apply what I know.</p>




<p>To further improve the ways I learn and think in an effort to be more well-rounded, it is important to consider what AS thinkers find difficult. For one, AS thinkers need time to deal with a subject thoroughly. To grow, especially knowing there will likely not always be enough time, I should make myself available for assignments and challenges that limit time but are within my scope of knowledge. This will hopefully provide me with opportunities to feel successful and allow me to understand that not every subject needs to be dealt with thoroughly to be done right.</p>




<p>Further, AS thinkers struggle with being forced to work with those of differing views and being diplomatic when convincing others. To improve my collaboration abilities, I should begin by listening and observing peers, those with differing views or those I want to convince. From listening and observing, I will likely gain insights and understandings about those with differing views that I could not gain otherwise. Further, I can use those insights in questions and any other points I need to make to be heard when it is my turn to speak.</p>


<p><small>
References:</p>

<p><li>1. <a href="http://web.cortland.edu/andersmd/learning/gregorc.htm">Mind Styles - Anthony Gregorc</a>
</li></p>

<p><li>2. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_styles#Anthony_Gregorc.27s_model">Wikipedia: Learning Styles</a>
</li></p>

<p><li>3. <a href="http://www.thelearningweb.net/personalthink.html">Personal Thinking Styles</a>
</li>
</p>
Other Resources:</p>

<p><li><a href="http://www.colorfulleadership.info/papers/concrete.htm"> Concrete - Abstract - Sequential - Random: Applying the Gregorc 4-Quadrant Model to Teamwork</a>
</li></p>

<p><li><a href="http://facstaff.gpc.edu/~jgutliph/Books/learning_styles/Abstract_Sequential.html">The Abstract Sequential Learning Style</a>
</li></p>

<p><li><a href="http://child-1st.typepad.com/my_weblog/2010/05/the-abstract-sequential-learning-style.html">The Abstract Consequential Learning Style</a>
</li></p>

<p><li><a href="http://www.ieslearning.co.uk/abseq.html">The Abstract Sequential Individual</a>
</li>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
