<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: wireframing | fmhub]]></title>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/categories/wireframing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fma2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-23T20:13:47-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://fma2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Farheen Malik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[comparing wireframes]]></title>
    <link href="http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/comparing-wireframes/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-27T18:55:35-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://fma2.github.io/blog/2014/04/27/comparing-wireframes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p>Here I consider web pages on the websites Google Drive, Twitter, and Digg Reader. While each website has more than one page, I will look at each site&rsquo;s default page, the page that appears when you go to their basic URL.
<ul>
<li>What problems does each page solve?</li>
<li>What visual challenges are there?</li>
</ul>
<h2>Google Drive</h2>
<img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-MQE5h_kZzBc/U11RZNY2WsI/AAAAAAAAT2g/DIrrHrn7PDE/w830-h687-no/Google+Drive+Wireframe+-+New+Page.jpeg" alt="Google Drive Wireframe">
<p>When I go to drive.google.com and log in to my Google account, the page that appears is Google Drive&rsquo;s &ldquo;My Drive&rdquo; page.</p>
<p>In order to understand the problems this page solves, it&rsquo;s important to first understand the purpose of Google Drive. Google Drive is an application that provides users with online, cloud-based storage space for all files&ndash;these files are accessible from smartphone, tablet, or computer, anywhere the user is. These files can be shared with friends, co-workers, etc., allowing for easy collaboration. Further, files (word processing, spreadsheet, presentation, etc.) can also be created, edited, shared on Google Drive.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;My Drive page lists a user&rsquo;s files or folders; it is the user&rsquo;s home base. From this page, a user can find documents they need to view, edit, and/or collaborate. If the document is not document is not immediately visible on the &#8220;My Drive&rdquo; page, the user can use the search tool at the top of the page to find it easily. The page is simple and looks much like a folder on a computer&rsquo;s hard drive looks with folders and setting options.</p>
<p>Despite its simplicity, there are a few visual challenges. Specifically, there is an expected learning curve for new Google Drive users. In order to understand the many uses of Google Drive, they must first add files to their Drive for any files to actually appear on the &ldquo;My Drive&rdquo; page. Further, the options (My Drive, Shared with Me, Starred) in the sidebar may not be immediately familiar, as they do not easily compare with what folders may look like on a computer&rsquo;s hard drive. In this sense, visually, the page is a challenge for those who do not understand the terms&ndash;though the page is fairly simple in design, the words could be overwhelming without an understanding of their meaning and uses.</p>
<h6>Link: <a href="drive.google.com" target="_blank">Google Drive</a>
</h6>
<h2>Twitter</h2>
<img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-WGdaT7oodYU/U11RZFH85RI/AAAAAAAAT2k/OL4CurZG4pI/w830-h687-no/Twitter+Wireframe+-+New+Page.jpeg" alt="Twitter Wireframe">
<p>When I go to Twitter.com and log in to my Twitter account, the page that appears is my &ldquo;Home&rdquo; page.</p>
<p>Twitter is considered a social networking and micro-blogging website. Users are able to send 140-character messages call &ldquo;tweets&rdquo;. On the &ldquo;Home&rdquo; page, a user is able read the tweets of other users they are following. These can appear on the Home page as they are sent, with the most recent tweet at the top of the tweets feed. Users have their own Twitter pages, on which all of their tweets are listed in order of when they were sent, and it would be burdensome for a user who wants to view the tweets of multiple users to have to go to each of their pages. Thus, it is important that a user also has the Home Page to see multiple user&rsquo;s tweets (with information on a multitude of topics) at once. Further, the Home page has a search tool to be able to find other users as well as find specific content (e.g. searching for tweets about Barack Obama after the State of the Union speech)</p>
<p>In my opinion, the main visual challenge of Twitter&rsquo;s home page is the constantly updating tweets feed. Within seconds, &ldquo;__ new Tweets&rdquo; will appear at the top of the tweets feed; after the user selects it, all of the tweets he/she was previously viewing will shift down the page and new tweets will appear on top. Though there may be images in these tweets, the majority of information presented in the old tweets and new tweets is in words. The Home page may lose impact if users are not reading any of the old or new tweets because there seems to be too much of it all.</p>
<h6>Link: <a href="twitter.com" target="_blank">Twitter</a>
</h6>
<h2>Digg Reader</h2>
<img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-0A3j4-I9FC0/U11RZNWaxXI/AAAAAAAAT2c/sPrgMjf7C18/w830-h687-no/Digg+Reader+Wireframe+-+New+Page.jpeg" alt="Digg Reader Wireframe">
<p>When I go to <a href="http://digg.com/reader">http://digg.com/reader</a> and log in to my account, the page that appears shows all articles from my subscribed feeds.</p>
<p>Digg Reader is &ldquo;a news aggregator operatd by Digg&rdquo; (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digg_Reader">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digg_Reader</a>). Users are able to subscribe to multiple sites through the Digg Reader site; they can then view news headlines/articles from these sites on a single page. Using Digg Reader makes it easy to keep track of news from multiple sources without having to go to every single news site. It is a one-stop shop.</p>
<p>If a user has subscribed to many news sites that update consisntetly through Digg Reader, the user&rsquo;s feed constantly updates. On the &ldquo;All&rdquo; articles page, headlines from all of these news sites appear in order of their posting with the newest first. If the user has subscribed to news sites which focus on different topics, all of these articles will still appear together in &ldquo;All&rdquo;. This can be a visual challenge, as it pushes too much information and too many topics onto a single screen with no images or many tools (beyond the Keyboard Shortcuts) to help the user digest the information.</p>
<h6>Link: <a href="http://digg.com/reader" target="_blank">Digg Reader</a>
</h6></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
